OK.
Maybe we shall get started.
This is the second of the
post-training lectures,
so we're going to talk about the
exciting developments in RLVR
or reinforcement learning
from verifiable rewards.
And I think this is in
some ways very timely.
I didn't get to
update the slide,
but there was just a
announcement by OpenAI folks
that they had solved one
of the major problems.
So that's a MyOpenMath
problem using
one of their thinking models.
How does that thing work?
That's exactly this thinking
model stuff or RLVR stuff.
And so thus far, where we're at
is we are at the left side here.
After we finished last lecture,
we've got instruction tuning,
we've got RLHF, we've got some
good stuff that's ChatGPT.
And what remains is the modern
developments in thinking models.
The model ability
to do very long COT
and solve these hard,
verifiable problems
like mathematics and coding
in some cases as well.
And remember that I ended last
lecture with this a little bit
of a downer note.
The RLHF wasn't
really going to get us
where we wanted to go because
of this problem called
overoptimization.
So we're going to go and collect
a bunch of preference data.
Preference data is very useful.
We will build some
reward model and then
we will RL against
that reward model.
But this thing is fundamentally
very annotation bottleneck
because we have a
reward model and you
can't keep putting compute
into the same reward model,
eventually you're going to
overfit your reward model.
And no matter how good of a
job you do at regularizing,
eventually you're going
to run into this problem
with overfitting.
And so really, this
is very depressing.
And it's not really
the potential
of reinforcement learning.
If you're a big reinforcement
learning believer,
you're going to look at
all things like AlphaGo
and so on where you say,
well, in these domains,
RL really did an amazing job.
What is the difference between
what we're doing in RLHF
and what has been
achieved in these more RL
native or RL natural domains?
And really the
difference, I would say,
or one major difference
between something like AlphaGo
and something like RLHF is that
in AlphaGo, we are optimizing
exactly what we want.
You get the win-loss
conditions of the game of Go.
You don't have any sloppiness
to that definition.
And so you can just put in
as much compute as you want.
And as long as the objective
improves, you're doing well.
In some sense, these
are search problems.
Whereas the top one is much
more of a learning problem.
Not quite a precise
distinction, but that's
one way of thinking about it.
So now there might be other
domains like formal mathematics
or even natural
language mathematics,
that have this flavor of being
more verifiable and therefore
much more amenable to
reinforcement learning.
So that's going to be the
motivation for why we're
going to study some of these.
And the algorithms aren't
going to be that different
fundamentally, but
where we will end up
will actually be
surprisingly different.
And so the lecture is going
to be in two parts today.
This mirrors a lot of
how we've structured
the course in other parts.
So in the first
part of the lecture,
I'm going to talk about
the core algorithms.
This is like basic
knowledge for you all.
You will use some of this
for your assignments.
And so I'm going to
talk about things what
is GRPO, how does PPO work.
And then after
I've done that, I'm
going to dig through a bunch
of open source releases
and show you how,
what I've taught you
in the first part of reflects
in the technical reports of many
of these major open
source model releases.
So we're going to dive in to
the methods and basic section.
And the first thing that I'm
going to start with is PPO.
We can't really discuss
RL for language models
without discussing PPO.
And even though
we've done it once,
PPO is confusing enough
that I think you will
benefit from doing it twice.
The most important
thing to identity,
let's say to remember in
RL for language modeling is
policy gradients.
And in particular this
reinforce gradient trick.
Well, we are always going to
be doing is gradient descent
on our rewards.
And we are going to do so by
taking essentially weighted SFT
updates.
The weights might be
positive or negative.
We will define what R is.
But this equation is important
because it will reappear
throughout this lecture.
This is in some sense
the core from which
everything else is derived.
Now, building upon
that, remember
that the intuition
from last lecture
was we want to take more
than one step at a time.
A policy gradient requires
us to sample from our policy
every time we want to
take a gradient step.
Can we reuse our rollouts?
Well, you can do TRPO.
You can do PPO and
so on and so forth.
I'll talk about PPO in a minute.
And I've already
talked about TRPO.
I won't really get
too much into this.
If you've taken RL
course, PPO is, of course,
well understood to you, like
you understand this algorithm,
but I don't assume that all
of you have taken RL class
and/or understand RL.
And so PPO, in case
you're not familiar,
is a real workhorse of RL.
It's been used in a variety
of very difficult RL settings.
OpenAI has done quite a few
of these in their early days
of being very RL pilled.
They had, this was
I think, OpenAI
gym where they were talking
about the PPO algorithm
and they're like,
hey, we can get
these people to walk around
using reinforcement learning.
In a much more dramatic
demonstration of this
was their OpenAI bot, which
they trained using PPO.
And so this can
excel with deep RL
in high-dimensional
action and state spaces,
where it's much more complicated
to do RL than it is usually.
Oh, yeah.
And there's the OpenAI
man running around.
All right.
So at a conceptual level,
PPO is actually very simple.
Remember that I told you, an
important part of all of this
is getting rid of PPO.
That's been a motivating
factor for a lot of people.
But if you look at
the pseudocode of PPO,
this is from the OpenAI's like
spinning up on RL documentation.
You look at this and you
say, this is not that bad.
This is actually pretty easy.
I could implement
this in one go.
You sample some trajectories.
I compute something called
an advantage using any method
of advantage estimation.
I clip the advantage in this
slightly strange but OK way.
And then I update the policy
under this clipped advantage.
And that's fine.
And then I can fit something
called a value function as well.
OK, fine.
This is all relatively
easy looking in practice.
And so I think because of this,
people are like, oh, it's OK.
PPO is totally fine.
But then you see blog
posts that look like this,
and this should strike
fear into your heart.
Because if you see a blog post
that says the 37 implementation
details of PPO,
you know that this
is an algorithm that is very
sensitive to your implementation
decisions.
And there's all sorts of
things that you can do
and all sorts of different
libraries and implementations,
and they give totally
different numbers
based on which ones you use.
And it turns out
that many people
have implemented this wrong.
And so there's paper
saying, like actually
the baselines that
some people use in PPO
aren't even baselines at all.
They fundamentally change
the optimization problem.
And so basically
because of this, I
think I would not be able to get
through the rest of the lecture
without telling you,
well, we actually
maybe need to start looking at
some implementations of PPO.
And the implementations
of PPO, let me tell you,
for language models are
not particularly pleasant.
This is, I mean, a very
good representative slide.
If anything, this is a
very good description
of what PPO looks like.
You've got advantage estimation.
This big block in the middle,
that's this advantage thing.
You've got an experienced
buffer because you're going
to keep some of the old stuff.
It's going to be training
this value model.
And the value models are being
used in the advantage estimation
calculation.
Notice how the green
box appears twice.
And importantly, some parts
of my objective, the KL term,
actually operates
token by token.
So it's not actually
just a bandit problem.
It's like a whole
multi-step RL problem.
And this is all very
difficult and complicated.
And so this has led to a variety
of really tricky implementation
things that you have to do.
And if you look at a
variety of implementations,
you find often that
there are things
that people do for PPO that are
a little bit strange and tricky
at times.
Let me see if I can find.
So one of my
students implemented
a PPO for a project a
while back doing RLHF.
So PPO, if you remember,
was used in RLHF.
And so we had this nice robust
reference implementation of PPO
and it took a long
time to get working.
So I looked into the details,
like what did we actually
do to get this thing to work.
The outer loop is fine.
The outer loop is something like
you go through your rollouts
and you're going to
take some PPO steps,
you're going to compute some
loss and clip some gradients
and take some steps.
Totally reasonable outer loop.
But then you start
of looking into it.
For now, the actual
inner compute loss part
follows almost exactly
the PPO update.
So this also looks mostly good.
We're computing things
like the advantages
and we're computing
the clipping ratios.
And then we're updating
the model based on that.
So this is all good.
But then you get to some
of the messier parts.
Actually, I'll
skip the rollouts,
where you have things
like well, maybe we
need KL penalties to
keep the original model
close to the reference,
but actually this
only works if you clip the
KL off at 0, which of course,
if you know anything about KL
divergences, that totally ruins
the point of a KL divergence.
You have both positive and
negative values being summed.
If you remove this, it
blows up immediately.
All things like this can happen.
This is not to say that this is
the way you should implement PPO
if you were doing it.
I think the reason why
I'm bringing this up
is to say implementations
for RL algorithms can
be somewhat tricky and somewhat
sensitive because of all
the moving pieces
in PPO, and because
of the high variance in
the gradient estimates.
These are all very, very tricky
things that are happening.
And, another thing
that you often see,
this one is not just
RL implementation.
It's very common.
In the original PPO
paper, you have this thing
called a generalized advantage
estimator that's basically
looking at this gamma discounted
reward, where you have
this value function
that's estimating
the reward at of every
token generation step.
But it turns out that
people often just
use gamma equals lambda
equals 1, which is just
a degenerate setting that turns
this back into a bandit problem.
So you've thrown away
a lot of the structure
that you get from PPO.
And so if you run this algorithm
after a bunch of engineering,
you will get what you expect.
And when you run your RL
algorithms for the assignment,
you should expect to see similar
things like the rewards go up.
The reward model rewards
go up if you're doing RLHF,
and then the negative
KL regularizers go down.
This is a reasonable
thing to expect to see.
But anyway, the
point of all of this
is to say implementation of
PPO can be quite painful.
Depending on the environment, it
can require hacks to stabilize.
All of this is painful.
Not to say that
it's not possible.
Lots of people have trained
very good models on PPO.
Many of the labs have
very turnkey solutions
for getting PPOs
to work at scale.
So this is not impossible.
But for people like researchers
who are implementing this
from scratch, PPO can just be
really finicky and complicated.
Another reason why PPO is
disfavored in many cases
is that it requires a value
model to estimate the value
at each token as you go.
And how big is the value model?
Well, it's as big as
the original model,
so this consumes some
memory that you would rather
be using for other stuff like
models or inference servers.
So now you might say,
well, in last lecture,
you told us about
this DPO thing,
and DPO seems pretty good.
Why don't we just use
DPO for everything?
Well, the problem is DPO
is a very specific solution
to a very specific problem.
DPO is good for pairwise
feedback in the form
of Bradley-Terry comparisons.
That is very specific.
And if I want to
solve math problems,
my math problems don't come in
the form of inherently pairwise
comparisons.
There are other
DPO variants that
are designed to break
that pairwise structure,
but really you're just using
the wrong hammer for the job.
You do not want to
use DPO necessarily
for what you would
normally use PPO for.
PPO is the more general hammer
that you can hit everything
with.
DPO is generally offline.
Although I think
this distinction
is very overstated
because it can
be made online by just
iterating DPO repeatedly.
So I don't think this is
necessarily a big difference.
So that's the context
for all of this.
And then so that
similarly to DPO,
there's just an enormous desire
by the research community
to not have to use PPO.
Hopefully, the fact that DPO
and GRPO have gotten adoption
tells you how painful it was to
get this to work in many cases.
And so GRPO much like
DPO, is the alternative,
it is the simpler way to
do RL for verifiable task.
It has taken over
for the most part
RLVR in the open
source, open knowledge,
let's call it community.
And it is very, very
similar to PPO in spirit.
It just strips out a couple
of the most complicated parts,
and by doing so, allows us to
have a much simpler algorithm.
So GRPO is by DeepSeek paper.
I think it was there
like DeepSeek math paper,
where you start with PPO.
It conceptually it says
PPO is a good idea,
but we want to change
just a few things.
And what does it change?
It changes arguably the most
complicated and annoying part
of PPO, which is
the value function.
So the value
function is the thing
that you subtract as a
baseline to reduce variance
of your gradient updates.
The value function is
a whole neural network.
It destabilizes training.
We don't want the value network.
So what do we do?
Well, we get rid of
the value network,
but we still need an advantage.
I don't want to do reinforce--
vanilla reinforce because
the variance of that
is going to be
really, really high.
So instead, what
we're going to do
is I'm going to
compute you advantage
as a z-score within a
group, and I'll explain
what that means in a moment.
But basically, the
idea is the following.
Normally, you look at
a reward that you get
and if you had a value
function, you would compare it
to your predicted value.
You would say, my
neural network says,
I should have
gotten a score of 5.
I got a score of 6.
So this is a good rollout.
That's usually what you do.
Instead, what you
would do is you
would let's say your
rollout with a score of 5.
You would now sample
10 other rollouts
and you would say, how
good was I compared
to my 10 other rollouts.
If I'm doing better
than my mean,
then I have a high advantage.
In some ways, a very natural
way of computing advantage
in contexts where you
can multiple sample
from the same prompt
or something like that.
So GRPO is exactly this idea.
If you look at the initial
definition of GRPO that
appeared in the
DeepSeek paper, you see,
this is the objective
that's being optimized.
They're going to do exactly
the PPO update, where they have
this min clipped
advantage, plus a KL term
to keep yourself close
to the reference.
And then KL is computed
in a particular way.
That detail is not
particularly important.
And importantly,
this advantage is
computed as a z-score over
samples of a group of outputs,
o of 1 through o of g.
So that's-- or within each
group, you have-- oh, sorry.
This advantage of i,
this is the place where
you compute the advantage.
What you do is you take the
reward over your rollouts
within each group,
you subtract the mean
and you divide by the
standard deviation.
So you get a z-score
for each group.
So in the online case and this
is an important distinction
because in many cases,
you may actually
end up running this online
rather than offline.
In the online case,
the clipping just
disappears because the ratio
between pi theta old and pi
theta is 1, this clipping
operator never does anything
and you just get
min a of i, a of i.
So this is just advantage
minus a KL penalty.
So I'm going to do RL
on my advantage, which
is defined by this.
So in the online
rollout case, it
is a very, very simple object
that makes sense as RL target.
So I can pause here
for a moment in case
any of the conceptual bits
of GRPO are not clear.
I mean, in some sense, this
is the foundation of all
of the exciting math stuff.
Or you can replicate all of the
exciting math stuff using GRPO.
So it's worth understanding
in a little bit of detail
before we move on to some
of the nitty-gritty details.
OK.
Good.
Simple enough that everyone
understands in one go.
I will take it.
And GRPO is very, very simple
because of the lack of value
function, you can basically
write down all of GRPO
in a very simple block of
code, where you just say,
I'm going to roll
out k times, I'm
going to compare my observed
rollout to those k references,
z-score it and then just
take a reinforced gradient
against those weights.
So you will write this
in your assignment.
And it's going to involve
a very simple set of steps.
Compute a reward for
each of your k rollouts.
Normalize your rollouts,
compute the KL term.
And then just take
gradient updates
on the combination of your
KL term and these rollouts.
You'll have to do a little bit
of thinking because in order
to do this using
autodiff, you will have
to do a stop grad somewhere.
But it's actually
not that complicated.
And you can see that you can
do a one-page implementation
of this basic idea.
And this is a reference
implementation of GRPO
that I took from
some folks at McGill,
which has a really nice little
toy version of this whole thing.
And the computation
of the group indices,
and the standard deviation
calculation and all of that
just fits in one
half of a slide.
The only thing that
they do differently
than the literal
paper write up of GRPO
here is they add a little
tiny weeny negative 4
to the standard
deviation calculation
to prevent it from
blowing up when you only
have a single sample, or
if your samples happen
to have the exact same rewards,
which does happen if you're
in a domain where you can get
exactly numerically 0 rewards,
like you failed to
solve a math problem.
But hopefully, this
emphasizes to you
how straightforward GRPO is,
and why almost all open source
work has been built
on this algorithm.
It's easy to implement,
easy to understand.
And if you, as we'll
see in the results,
it provides fairly
compelling results
in terms of emulating a lot of
what the closed source labs have
done using potentially PPO.
So how well does it work?
In the original
DeepSeek math paper,
which if you're
into math AI stuff,
I would encourage
you to read, it's
a nice and really
interesting set of results.
They show that GRPO, the
yellow and the blue lines,
does much better than RFT,
like rejection fine tuning.
You'll implement this
as a baseline as well.
That's just taking
the correct answers
that your model generates
and training on them
and throwing away
everything else.
And they seem to show
process supervision, which
is grading not just
the final answer,
but grading the intermediates
give you some gains.
I'll talk more about that later.
That is an important
thing to discuss and cover
because that's one of
the big design decisions
for these kinds of RL problems.
But for now, you can
just internalize the fact
that GRPO works.
The blue and yellow lines
are above the others.
OK.
So now let's think a little bit
more about the GRPO objective.
What is happening
in this objective?
Are we actually taking
policy gradients?
There are important conceptual
questions that we should really
think through.
And so if we think about the
difference between GRPO and PPO,
remember that PPO had this
value function thing which
feeds into the advantage.
And in GRPO, we strip
that out and we replace
that with the z-score guy.
This a of i, ratio
of r minus mean
divided by standard deviation.
So is this a good advantage?
I think for those of you that
have been in an RL class,
you already know the
answer to this question.
Is this a good
advantage function?
What makes a good advantage?
What makes a valid
advantage function?
Well, if you look at Sutton
and Barto, the big classic book
for reinforcement
learning they will say,
well, there's this algorithm
called reinforce with baseline.
And the things
you're allowed to do
is that if you're doing
policy gradients, which
is this line over here,
this very first equation.
I want to take my gradient step
on the direction of my rewards.
And the thing you can do is
you can take your rewards
and I can subtract
any-- what they
call state-dependent baseline,
in this case, our state.
If we're in the bandit
world, it's just the prompt.
So you can have a
prompt-dependent baseline
that you can subtract.
And anything that does
just this is a valid form
of a policy gradient.
So you're still going to
descend in the same direction
as long as you do this.
And depending on
your choice of b,
you will either have
lower or higher variance
in doing this gradient
descent process.
Now, you should probably
notice that what we're doing
is not this.
We are not just subtracting
a constant value,
we are also dividing by
the standard deviation.
And so that is a problem.
It turns out well, it's
in some ways a problem.
In other ways, it's not.
If you really want a
conceptually clear algorithm
that really does what's
written on the tin,
it actually descends the reward.
GRPO does not do that.
Because as I've
highlighted in red here,
GRPO divides by the
standard deviation, which
breaks this baseline contract.
We're not just dividing
or subtracting a baseline.
We're also normalizing
by the standard deviation
of my rewards.
Of course, there's another
thing that GRPO does,
which I didn't mention earlier.
As an implementation detail
that is tricky, which is GRPO
does this almost per token.
So they'll divide by the
total length of the sequence
as a normalization factor.
But if you try to derive
GRPO from first principles,
following the policy gradient
and baseline theorems,
you'll end up with
something different.
You won't have a
length normalizer
and you won't have the standard
deviation normalization.
And some folks soon after
GRPO came out noticed this,
and they wrote a paper
basically saying, well,
if you don't do these two
things that are different,
then you get very
different potentially very
positive behavior.
I will talk about that.
Also, when we get to the--
not OpenAI, sorry
DeepSeek R1 paper.
But the main thing
here is to say
GRPO is not the first principles
derivation of this idea.
It is actually doing
something slightly different
with both pros and cons.
So what are these
two terms doing?
We now that GRPO is not
actually directly descending
on the reward objective.
We know that it has these
two correction factors.
What do they do?
Well, the length normalization
is easier to see.
So what are we doing?
We are dividing longer
sequences with a bigger number.
And so what this
will do is that it's
going to encourage
the model to generate
long outputs because-- or
sorry when you're wrong
it will encourage you to
generate wrong outputs.
Because let's say--
I know that I'm going
to get a math proof wrong.
I'm going to incur my negative
reward of let's say, negative 1.
I'm just going to generate
an infinitely long string.
If I do that, I'll get
to divide by infinity,
and I'll get to totally get
rid of my negative penalty.
That's an extreme case.
But you understand that if
you divide by the output,
you encourage the model to blab
on once it realizes that it
cannot actually
solve the problem.
So this is a length problem
that you end up getting.
If you fix that,
you'll find that often
what people have observed in
GRPO COT, like chain of thought,
thinking length growing
and growing and growing,
that actually turns out to
just cap off at a constant
rather than just continually
and forever grow.
So this seems like a
potentially good thing.
And especially on
the incorrect cases,
you really don't want
to be generating longer
and longer and longer outputs.
So the standard
deviation normalization,
this one's a little
bit more complicated.
But if you think about
it, what I'm doing
is I'm dividing by the
standard deviation.
And so this can be
thought of as emphasizing
problems where the standard
deviation is small.
And when is my
standard deviation
small for a binary
reward problem?
Well, that's when the problems
are too easy or too hard.
If my problem is really easy
and I get 100% all the time,
I'm going to divide by
1 over or the number--
I'm going to divide
by basically 0
because there's 0 variation if
I always get a question correct.
Similarly, if I always
get a question wrong,
I have 0 variation
in my rewards.
I'm going to upweight
that significantly.
So the standard deviation term
is upweighting the two sides,
both easy and hard questions.
That seems like clearly
a thing that maybe we
don't want because we want our
models to potentially learn
on things that are within
its solvability range.
So that's the algorithmic
components of RLVR.
And I'm going to
go through several
of the different
recent model releases
and talk through all the
algorithmic components
that I think are quite
important, including some
of the stuff that I added this
year that's new, which is really
the agentic stuff that I
think has been catching on
and is increasingly important
for using and deploying
these models.
But before I do that,
I can pause here
and if anyone has
algorithmic questions,
I'll take them before I move on.
OK.
Good.
All right.
So we're going to
start with DeepSeek R1
because I think this is a
bit of a social phenomenon.
I think everyone should know
a bunch about DeepSeek R1.
I think it's a lovely
paper kicked off
the wave of open
source RLVR models.
And what's remarkable
about it, I
think it was really
the first thing
to have matched
OpenAI O1's behavior.
So the key things
about OpenAI O1
was you have very long
chains of thought.
It's clearly RL, and you
have really good performance
on hard math problems.
And they also provided RL
recipe that anyone could do.
And I think from the perspective
of R&D, this is very important.
If your solution was like
you have this horrible PPO
thing that no one
but DeepSeek can run,
then that is much less of
an impact, at least for us
researchers than this
kind of GRPO thing,
which anyone can really
play with, even you
in your assignments.
And finally, they have some
really interesting distillation
insights that I think
have held up even now.
So the starting point
of DeepSeek R1, and I
think you can see how a
lot of DeepSeek's expertise
build on each other.
So they had this
DeepSeek math paper,
where they were doing GRPO.
They had already understood
a lot of the nuances of RL
on math problems.
And so because of
this, they started off
with a lot of the
components of DeepSeek math.
But one of the really
important differences, and I'll
highlight an expert
just because I
think it's particularly
important is they abandon
process supervision, which was
the thing that worked really
well in DeepSeekMath,
and they go only
with outcome supervision.
And just to be clear,
outcome supervision
is when you have reward only
for whether the final answer is
correct or incorrect.
And process supervision is when
you have a grading rubric, let's
say, to check the validity of
intermediate steps in a proof.
A lot of people thought process
supervision was important.
Turned out it wasn't
critical for a lot of things.
So R1 was interesting
in that it has
a lot of different components.
But one of the very
interesting components
is R1 zero, where
they don't really
do that much post training,
so they have a base model.
Of course, the base
model, as we all now
is also [? MIT ?] trained.
And so this guy can do some
amount of instruction following.
And then on top of
this base model,
they do basically RLVR, where
the rewards for their GRPO
algorithm is accuracy, rewards
for whether they correctly
solve a collection of math
problems and format rewards.
And this one is important
because the format rewards
basically allow them to strip
out the chain of thought later.
They want the model
to properly use
thinking tags to
enclose their COT.
But this is a very
simple recipe.
GRPO is very simple.
Accuracy rewards
are very simple.
In fact, you will
implement and replicate
essentially the set of
results in some ways,
and you do just this
very simple recipe.
And where do you end up?
Well, you end up something
that is only a little bit worse
than OpenAI O1.
So this is really,
really, really clean.
And I like this
result because it
has none of the messes of a
real production post-training
pipeline thrown in.
You don't really
question whether oh,
was it because of the RLHF
helping or this or that.
It's a very simple
base model plus GRPO.
Your math abilities
are quite good.
And I think R1 also
took off, partially
because of the
interesting phenomena
they claim to have
observed in the paper.
So one of the things they
claim to have observed
is as we go longer
and longer and longer
during training, the model
is able to think for longer
and longer and longer.
Their COT get longer
And they also highlighted
this thing that I believe
went viral on social media,
which is like the aha moment,
where the model is if
you train it for enough,
its COT is able
to do things like,
oh, there's an aha moment
that I can flag here.
And they thought this
was really interesting.
It is unclear to me whether
either of these phenomena
are really particularly
impressive in many ways.
We now know that longer CoTs
is arguably a natural side
effect of the length
normalization of the GRPO
algorithm.
And the aha moment
others have showed
is actually appears in
even the base model.
And so clearly, it can't just
be a result of the RL algorithm.
Lots of people say
aha, I can use this
as part of solving
the math problem.
The model has learned
it during pre-training.
It's not surprising at
all that somehow during RL
just happens to get
extracted because it's
emitting a lot of math tokens.
So I think the phenomena
that was highlighted
is not particularly
salient or exciting,
but I do think R1 was a really
important milestone in that it
highlighted just how
simple RLVR could be.
This is very, in some
sense clean as an algorithm
and as a way of solving these
really difficult problems.
And so R1 zero was this very
nice, clean controlled setting.
And then R1 was their attempt
to productionize this system.
And I think one thing
that's nice about R1
and I'll show you
the Qwen equivalent
later, is you can see how you
stack all the pieces together.
I think we've studied all
the pieces in isolation.
We know where pre-training is.
We know that there's
RLHF, we know SFT,
but how do we compose
all of the pieces
to actually get a
system at the end?
Well, usually the thing that
you do is something like,
well, we have our
mid-trained model,
we're going to do a bunch
of reasoning training, maybe
some long context
extension somewhere too.
And then we're going
to do RLHF at the end,
because that's in some sense,
the most user-facing object.
We want to make sure that the
formatting and all of this
is nice.
RLHF can very much
help with that process.
One of the other things
that they did was they
added a language consistency
reward for the chain of thought
for their production model.
I think if I remember
the report right,
this was because
the R1 zero style
training without a
consistency reward
would language switch
in COT, and they
thought this was very
uninterpretable and slightly
disturbing.
And so they wanted to
just have it output
a single consistent language.
And so they do this just for
interpretability reasons.
And then they have some of
the non-verifiable rewards
as well, thrown
in to GRPO, almost
as blending into
the RLHF process,
but otherwise it's a
very, very similar thing.
And the whole pipeline, I
think, is very straightforward.
So for SFT, what they
do is pretty simple.
So in R1 zero, they don't
want to do any SFT at all.
But in R1, they're willing
to do long COT data.
And when you're reading these
open source tech reports,
it's fun to try to
read between the lines.
When they say something
like, we construct
and collect a small
amount of long COT data,
you might wonder--
I wonder if that was distilled
from some other models.
That is a particularly
like negative thing
for open source models.
Everyone is nowadays doing
this, but I just find it funny
that it's very carefully
written collect a small amount
of long COT data.
And so this is used to
fine tune the model.
We know that for a very good
base model, just SFT on long COT
can unlock a lot of
O1 style capabilities.
And that's a great
starting point for RL.
So they start there and then
they add some verification
to filter out the CoTs.
And then they continue
on with processing.
And I think many
papers since then,
some including some
from my students
have shown things
that if you have
the right kind of
distillation procedure
and you have the right
kinds of base model,
you can basically get a lot of
the long COT reasoning juice
just from SFT.
And I think this is
maybe interesting
because one of the
things that I think
is still an open question
is, do you really
need RL for some of this.
And I think maybe one way of
thinking about the role of RL
in language modeling
is that RL is
a great source of supervision.
If you're solving
frontier math problems,
you just don't have
the supervision
to get detailed long
CoTs, and RL allows
you to self-generate that.
But once someone has
generated these long CoTs,
you could potentially
also learn from imitation.
And that seems to be what a lot
of these distillation results
partially show.
So the RL part for R1 is
basically the same as R1 zero.
Minus the language consistency
loss that I mentioned,
it's basically just we run
the RL training using GRPO.
And that leads to
essentially the final phase,
which is what we learned
about last lecture.
So we do some basic instruction
tuning style SFT and then RLHF.
For non-verifiable tasks, they
basically use the same thing
as DeepSeek V3.
So there's really no
surprises at all here.
How well does it work?
It's really, really good.
And I think this is the
reason why there was all
that panic or big
noticing of DeepSeek
because R1 was genuinely
a very good model.
It beat O1 on many
of the categories.
It matched a lot of the
test time scaling behavior
that people expected.
And it came from a
very simple recipe.
So it was very easy
to understand where
the gains were coming from.
And the last thing related
to some of the distillation
discussions that I was saying
is you can then take R1's CoTs
and you could put
it into Qwen 2.5,
and if you did so, you could
really significantly boost
the performance of these models.
In some cases, matching a lot
of these specialized thinking
models.
And so in other
words, really, if you
can get the right
kinds of long CoTs
that are legible
to these models,
often it is possible
to get them to reason
for long periods of time, like
the base models are already
surprisingly good, and this
works even for Llama models
as well, which I think
is quite fascinating.
So to close out
the DeepSeek saga,
I quite liked a lot of
the DeepSeek tech reports,
because they often
do both ablations
and they also tell you failed
things that didn't work.
And if you've been following
what they've been doing,
DeepSeekMath has all of this
process reward model stuff.
It's like we got to
verify all the steps
and then you read R1 and you
say where did the process reward
models go.
Well, they tell you where
the process reward models go,
which is we tried to get
process reward models to work.
They just didn't do
very much for us.
It turns out that outcome
reward models are great
and they're good enough.
And you can scale the data
for those a lot better.
I think a big
debate for PRMs was,
where are you going to get
these step-by-step rubrics.
And it's very hard
to scale that up.
I think at this point,
it's quite clear now
that outcome reward models
are very, very good.
And that's the bulk of where
the action is happening.
Similarly, if you were around
for the initial O1 release,
a lot of people speculated
about what was going on
inside OpenAI's O1.
They were like, oh,
are they doing PRMs?
Are they doing tree
search like AlphaGo?
They to tried a lot
of MCTS and they
describe we couldn't get
it to work very well.
I just very much
want to highlight
and the fact that they're
very open about all
these explorations and
the things that they tried
and didn't work, rather than to
say they didn't try it at all.
Cool.
All right.
And if I talk about--
or actually, I'll pause
here in case anyone
has questions, although
I don't know if-- yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] you should explain
the positive reward basis
by [INAUDIBLE] Because I
thought you said for negative,
like we encourage to divide
by infinity and [INAUDIBLE] 0
for positive.
Yeah.
So the question was
like for positive cases
what the length normalizer do.
And of course, in those
cases, the length normalizer
encourages you to shorten
the COT, which is good
if you want to save
on inference costs,
bad if that degrades
your accuracy.
But I think the main issue
is that for the long--
for the negative ones, you
get some really long responses
and the positive cases,
it can't shrink it
that much because there's
a lower bound to how small
your COT can go to solve
a particular problem.
I guess I'm trying to
understand that explanation
for the diagram.
Is that--
I think doctor GRPO has a
cleaner diagram of this.
So in the R1 diagram,
this is all aggregated.
This is all of the responses
across their evals.
It's not just the positive ones.
But if we look at the
doctor GRPO plot over here.
So this is like the average
output length and this
is the incorrect output length.
And so you see that in the
correct output length is here.
So you see somewhat
that this is really
being driven by
the incorrect ones
as we would expect
from the explanation.
So the story, at least in these
sets of controlled comparisons,
is quite clean and clear.
Yeah.
Cool.
So now, I'm also going to talk
about an alternative method,
Kimi K1.5 or alternative
paper and approach.
And I always feel like
when I talk about R1,
I'm obligated to talk about
Kimi K1.5 because they came out
at the same time as R1.
They also beat R1, and yet
everyone is all about DeepSeek,
and Kimi is not quite as often
brought up in the conversation,
even though their models
are extremely good.
And I'm not just talking about
them out of pity, per se.
I think Kimi has this nice
thing that they do something--
some sets of things, quite
differently than DeepSeek,
and we can learn quite a
bit from the fact that both
of these work.
I think this is part of the
theme of this class, which
is by reading all of
these tech reports
and by looking at
broader patterns,
we can roughly
start to understand
what are the valid
or easy spaces to get
these algorithms to work.
So they do actually
quite a bit more
detail in talking about the data
set construction and curriculum
generation for the RL
process, which many have said
is quite important.
And they also have a
different RL algorithm,
which in some ways,
has similar intuitions
but is not exactly GRPO.
And so this is another nice
validation that technically
speaking, I don't
think you necessarily
need something like GRPO
to get these guys to work.
So the first part I want
to talk about is the data.
The data remains very important
for all of these processes.
And for RL, there's
an additional wrinkle
of curriculum, what
difficulties of problems
do you want to throw in?
In SFT, you don't really
think about difficulty
very much because you just
jam the data in there.
For whatever data that
you want, you just
do pre-training
losses and the model
is forced to learn from these.
In SFT, there's a little
bit more of a subtlety.
We talked quite a bit about
the hallucination issues,
and maybe sometimes
you don't want
to train on some of this data.
But for RL, there's
this additional wrinkle
that if your problems are
too hard, you get no rewards.
And if you get no rewards,
you have no signal.
And if you have no
signal, you can't learn.
So it's very important
to have broad coverage
of the right kinds of examples.
And so what the Kimi
folks do is first of all,
they try to get a whole big,
broad range of coverage of data.
Unsurprising, they
exclude multiple choice
because that's covered in
lots of different domains.
They want things that
require long, deep thought.
And their argument is
maybe multiple choice
doesn't have that.
But maybe this last
one I think is maybe
the most important idea.
This appears in a lot
of different RL papers.
You basically filter all
the examples for things
that either pass or
sorry, you filter them
based on a best of k filter.
So here you take examples.
And if they succeed
on best of 8,
if you sample eight
times and the model
can do it at least once, then
that's not a great RL example,
because it's already at the edge
of the model's capabilities.
You're not going to teach it
anything particularly new.
And so you only look at examples
that basically fail this test,
because that allows
us to essentially pick
the right kinds of problems.
And so this saves compute.
It allows you to skip
problems entirely.
You can also filter
on both sides
to get problems that are
neither too hard nor too easy.
I think the general consensus
in the research community
is that doing this medium
range difficulty filtering
is very good if
really what you want
is for RL to progress
at a steady pace.
As with DeepSeek no
description about SFT.
We can speculate
about what that is,
but we have no
concrete information.
So I think the interesting
thing about Kimi
is that they have a
DPO inspired argument,
but they end up actually
in a place that's
very similar as GRPO.
And I think the fact that
they end up in similar places
is suggestive of which
of these components
are potentially useful if you're
designing a new RL algorithm,
for example.
So they start at the exact
same place as everyone else.
So this should now look
very familiar to all of you.
It's just maximize the expected
reward under my policy.
And I've got this KL
regularizer on the right that
keeps me close to my
base policy, or maybe
even the previous
iterations policy,
depending on how you're going
to do this-- do this RL.
So they're going to follow the
same DPO style derivation, where
they say assume that I
can maximize analytically
and I solve for the
reward model that
does that maximization
or corresponding
to that maximization.
And that's going to give
me this ratio of policies.
And I'm going to plug that back
in to my objective up there
and try to solve for
what is happening.
Well, what they're
now saying is they
want to try to match
the reward model.
And for this
equality to be-- they
want this equality to be true,
which is true at the minimizer.
And therefore, this
is a big heuristic.
If something's equal
at the minimizer,
why don't we just put a
squared loss on that thing
and minimize the squared loss?
I think optimization
people looking at this
would be horrified
at this, but I
think this is a totally
reasonable intuition
in some ways.
We know that these two
things should be close
when the model is good.
So it is also maybe OK
to treat making those two
things explicitly
close as a surrogate.
This derivation, as you can
see, is very, very different
from GRPO.
We're not going through the
PPO path to derive this update.
But now, actually,
lo and behold,
you take a gradient
of this L, you
end up with something that
looks surprisingly like GRPO
with an added regularizer term.
What you end up
with is this thing
that is a policy gradient
with a baseline R bar.
And that R bar is actually
the mean of each condition,
these x's.
And you have this
additional regularizer term,
which is essentially the KL
term that would appear in GRPO.
So in some sense,
we've reinvented
the group mean
normalized baseline
through quite different means.
And so the Kimi folks
I think in some ways
had a nicer or better view
of the length problem.
I think the GRPO
folks were like,
isn't it great that the length
is growing uncontrollably.
I'm sure our model
is being smarter.
That's a little bit of
an uncharitable take,
but when you present this
plot as a positive thing,
the implied statement
is like, it's great
that our model is
thinking for longer.
But the Kimi folks look
at this long COT problem
and they say, well, if we're
making long CoTs potentially,
that's very wasteful.
We don't really want long CoTs
because CoTs cost inference.
So not only do they not
have a length problem,
because if you look
at this objective,
they don't normalize
by sequence length,
but they actually want
to go even further
and they want to compress
the length of the response.
And this is another
important feature
that we see generally occurring
in language model development.
We want the CoTs to be
as short as possible.
We want to solve hard problems.
We don't want to
think for very long,
because when we
we have to essentially
subsidize the user.
If you're OpenAI and your
users have the $200 Pro Plan,
and your models are
thinking for an hour
at a time, that's not a
very good place to be in.
Whereas if your
models are thinking
for five minutes at a time,
that is a great place to be in.
And so for all of
these reasons, Kimi
wants to go and
compress the CoTs.
How do you do that?
Well, the simplest
are all thing to do
is you come up with a
heuristic length reward
and you just tack it
on to the RL process.
This reward is
surprisingly complicated.
And the thing that
they're doing is
you're trying to make longer
sequences shorter and shorter.
Correct answers also
should be short.
The interesting
balance here is if you
make the incorrect
answers too short,
they no longer have
a way to recover.
So let me give you an example.
Imagine I'm bad at geometry.
AI bad at geometry, I get
lots of incorrect answers,
and the penalty makes my
geometry CoTs really short.
Now, my geometry CoTs are 0.
I'm really bad at geometry.
I will never recover from this.
I will never get a positive
geometry reward ever again.
And I'm stuck.
And so what you do is you don't
force the incorrect answers
to be super short.
You incentivize them to be
just a little bit shorter
than the average, so
that the incorrect stuff
doesn't grow unboundedly.
And so this has, in the end,
a surprisingly reasonable set
of outcomes.
And so as I said before, they
have a really nice RL set
of views on how they do
their data set curation.
So not only do they have this
data set that they filter,
they also look at
the success rates
of how often they're able to
solve particular problems.
And once the model masters
a particular problem,
it gets taken out
of the problem set.
So you save some
compute doing that.
I think basically everyone
doing RL does these success rate
filtering to avoid
both wasting compute
or working on problems that
are way too hard for the model.
And they basically have
rewards that, for code, they
take ground truth solutions
and they generate some new test
cases.
And for math, they actually
have a reward model
to check for answer
equivalence checks.
And this is a really
funny thing in some ways,
because we started
out this lecture
by saying we want to work
on formal math or something,
something truly
verifiable, where you can--
a compiler can check the
correctness of your math.
And then we've gone through
most of the lecture.
And then in the end,
where we ended up?
Well, we ended up
with a reward model,
a reward model that checks the
correctness of math answers.
Once again, you'll see
why in the assignment
or maybe if you play with the
assignment, you'll see why.
You'll quickly find out that
answer equivalence checking
is a very difficult problem.
Because in math, you can write
equivalent things in many ways.
And not only that,
a language model
can give the answer
back in many ways.
Even if you prompt it to
say give the answer back
in latex boxed, maybe
sometimes it skips the boxed,
maybe add some extra
stuff to the box.
There are lots of ways
that the model can just
fail to get the right answer by
a strict correctness checker,
even though it has
the right idea.
And so for these reasons,
basically, most RL projects
have a very complicated
answer checker, either a regex
or a model, or who
knows what in order
to avoid these
kinds of problems.
It's a real rabbit hole getting
the verified part of RLVR.
Cool.
The last thing which connects
to some of the systems bits
that we had talked about
earlier and the inference bits
is RL optimization.
And RL infra is
really quite hard.
Training is hard and
inference is hard.
And RL puts the two together.
So in some ways, no wonder is it
really horrible and difficult.
Even worse, I think one of the
things that you don't initially
appreciate about how hard
it is to make RL efficient
is think of the
following scenario.
Now, imagine you've
got your rollouts,
but you've got one
really hard math problem,
let's say one of them is
like the Riemann hypothesis.
And your model is
really chugging along
on the Riemann hypothesis.
It's got this gigantic COT.
Now, what's happening?
In the meantime, if you're
doing naive inference,
everyone else is waiting
on this one rollout
to complete in order to
move on to the next phase.
So if you're doing
these batch things,
long rollouts can
really hurt you.
And so RL really needs to
deal with all of these really
tricky low-level details.
So you need to
deal with the fact
that some CoTs can
get really long.
Do you need to truncate
them, do you somehow
set them into a different
machine, who knows?
These are all decisions
that you can make.
If you switch from training
to rollouts, you roll out once
and then you train and you
roll out and you train,
you have to somehow
deal with this.
Either some of your machines
are pure rollout machines,
and some of them are
training machines,
or you're switching out
frameworks all the time.
Both of them are very costly.
And then finally, you have this
really difficult and horrible
trade off, which is on policy
stuff is mathematically
and training dynamics
wise very nice.
So GRPO in its simple on policy
form behaves very nicely.
You will experience
this in your assignments
and then you will get greedy.
You will say but my systems
utilization is so low.
I could do so much better if
only I could reuse my rollouts,
then I can overlap my
inference and computation
and do all clever things.
And so you will attempt
to reuse these rollouts.
And that will lead to
off-policy problems which
then lead to destabilizing
your training
and all sorts of things
that are very difficult.
So these are all sorts
of things that end up
getting very, very tricky.
And so I think most open
source technical reports will
have these days a section
talking about their RL infra,
and their RL infra
is going to have
to have both a training part.
That's the blue boxes over here
and an inference part, which
is the green part on the right.
And you're going to have to move
weights from the training part
to the inference part.
So you need some of story
for how to move those around.
And you need to
coordinate them closely.
And in some cases,
maybe they even
share the same machines because
as inference is running,
the training one might be idle.
So all of these
are complexities.
And you have lots of very
complicated systems things
to do.
So we already know that
Kimi beats OpenAI O1,
but we also see some
really nice things
showing that as RL proceeds,
you're able to think longer
and performance goes up.
But in some cases, it's
not that we're just
unboundedly increasing tokens.
We end up getting
cases where I think
OmniMath is a good example.
You're not thinking
for that much longer,
but your performance
continues to go up.
So maybe this is a good example
of this length control kicking
in and doing good things.
The final thing I want to talk
about is you might wonder,
is this actual RL
stuff much better
than just training
on correct answers.
This is called expert iteration.
It worked very well in
a number of past papers.
In cases where you're dealing
with very unstable stuff,
you may actually want to do
expert iteration instead.
Kimi K1 has very
large scale ablations
showing that these
kinds of RL methods
work consistently better
than expert iteration.
So that's the orange
beating the blue over here.
So you can't really avoid RL
if you want to squeeze out
all of your performance.
I can pause here
in case anyone has
questions about the Kimi stuff.
And then I'll move on
to the last of the three
which is Qwen 3.
Great.
OK.
So the last one that I want to
talk about is Qwen 3 and also
Qwen 3.5-Next-Coder.
The names are
getting complicated.
And Qwen 3 is later.
But they have actually really
interesting scaling and data
results.
So I want to talk about those.
And the successor to this,
which is Qwen 3.5-Next-Coder is
interesting because I think has
the most details of I would say
agentic RLVR training out of the
major tech reports and they do
lots of cool things.
So once again, as
with DeepSeek, one
of the nice things that we
see with the Qwen report
is the full way that all
of these are organized.
And this is very similar
to the DeepSeek structure.
We do base model to basically
SFT, then reasoning RL.
And then they have this
thinking mode fusion.
I'll talk about that later.
And then they do
RLHF and then they
have a model that gets shipped.
But of course, they don't
want to serve that directly.
So they do distillation to
get their smaller models.
I mean, Qwen 3 is quite a
respectable open source model.
You can basically have this
be your mental picture of how
frontier-ish language
models are built putting
all the components together.
And I think you would have
a pretty reasonable picture
of what is happening.
And Qwen uses basically, at
this point, tried and tested
playbook for RLVR.
I think they take lots of the
best parts of Kimi and DeepSeek,
and they get it right.
They do a lot of filtering
for difficulty because we
know that saves compute.
That's a good way
to get good data.
They also do other things,
like they remove things
that the model can
get right without COT
because we know that's
not a thinking problem.
They remove things that are
too similar to validation data
to try to decontaminate things.
And then they do a little
bit of manual filtering
on reference CoTs.
Maybe most remarkably about Qwen
3 is they actually do their RL
on very few examples,
just 4,000 examples.
But once again, if you have
the rest of the pipeline right,
you can actually get
surprisingly far.
So the core of the
RLVR components
are maybe not super surprising
because they are really
building off of DeepSeek
R1 and also Kimi.
There are some interesting Qwen
3 specific things, some of which
they've ended up getting rid of,
but I think some of the ideas
are actually quite interesting.
So one of the
things that they do
is they mix thinking and
non-thinking things with tags.
And that's how they end up
having a thinking mode, where
the model has a long
COT and they can mix
that with a non-thinking mode.
So both the instant response
model and the long COT model
basically live in
the same model.
This was not true in many cases.
There was often a thinking
mode and a non-thinking model,
even at OpenAI.
They also have--
I thought this was
quite interesting,
which is they have this way of
early exiting thinking where
if they append a special string,
they'll immediately stop the COT
and the model is forced to give
an answer to whatever prompt
is given.
We see this even in-- we see
this affordance in interfaces
like ChatGPT, where you're able
to terminate the thinking early
and try to get an immediate
answer, for example.
But what we see with
this and I've always
thought this was a surprising
an interesting thing, which
is that as you vary the
thinking budget, doing
this early termination
trick, you end up
finding that the
performance of the model
degrades gracefully, even though
at the lower-thinking budgets,
these models are kind of
getting truncated mid-thought,
they're able to give
surprisingly reasonable
responses even at that point.
And we see that
consistently, even
with very small-thinking
budgets, the thinking
mode models are
much better on all
of these mathematical
or coding tasks
compared to the instant
response mode, which
is much more of the classic
instruction following plus RLHF
models.
And so you can-- one of the nice
things they do for us is look
at the contribution of all
of the different components
to performance.
And in many ways, this
is not something that
should surprise you too much.
If you do this reasoning
RL and then general RL,
you're able to slowly
get improvements
in all of the different
tasks, things like Arena-Hard
or CounterFactQA.
These are general tasks for
which you want more normal RF,
and we see significant
boosts to that performance
across the board.
There are some degradations
that we see in math and coding
because we fuse together
non-thinking components,
but the degradation
is not so bad.
I think, actually, even
though these numbers
in an absolute sense are
small in later releases,
I think in some of
the Qwen 3.5, they've
gone back on fusing
both thinking
and non-thinking
into a single model.
I think what-- they used to call
this hybrid models because they
found this drop unacceptable.
They wanted to squeeze
out all the juice
possible on thinking modes.
And so they've now,
I think, separated
these models from each other.
The very last topic and paper
that I want to cover is Qwen 3--
or sorry, I flipped the two.
It's Coder-Next not Next-Coder,
which is one of the newer models
to come out.
And I think if you're
interested in general agent
stuff, of course, there's
other agents things
to think about harnesses.
But if you're interested in how
do you actually build an agent.
This is probably a
good report to go read.
Qwen3-Coder-Next great
agent post-training paper.
But in some ways,
post-training for an agent
is not very different from
everything that we've described.
It's not like there's a new
agent training algorithm.
Really, you should
internalize this lesson
throughout the entire class.
Data is the important thing.
So if you're going to train an
agent or post-training an agent,
what are you going to do?
You're going to get
the data together.
So there's two
parts to the data.
To get a lot of
the capabilities,
you can't just inject
them at the end.
You have to probably start
a little bit earlier.
And so there's an extensive
mid-training phase
that happens to try
to get as much coding
and agent like capabilities
into the model as possible.
So they'll do
things like they'll
take repositories and
concatenate the files
in the repository to generate
these very long context data
and put it into the model.
We know that the
model is eventually
going to see these very
long COT traces, where
maybe the agent has opened
a bunch of files, very
useful pre-training style data.
They take pull
requests and then they
try to construct
synthetic context for it,
using RAG that is potentially
helpful for understanding
the pull request.
That all goes in
the mid training.
They will take documents that
they detect using an automated
method to have text and
code, and then they'll
use an LLM to transform this
to a nice markdown format.
Throw that all in as well.
And then finally, they're going
to have a language model, talk
about coding on web documents
that are coding related
to generate coding-ish
synthetic data,
and then they'll take
publicly-available coding
agents, run them on
various environments,
which I'll describe later.
And the traces of those runs
all go into mid training.
They'll do some fairly
standard stuff as well,
like instruction
following, and they'll
have an additional
task, which I think
is not super relevant for us
for filling in the middle.
If you're coding and you want
to fill in the middle of a span,
it's useful to
have that ability.
So they throw some of that
data into mid training.
But otherwise, this is a very
standard but in-depth data
collection procedure
to try to get
some of these agentic
abilities into mid training.
And then the Qwen
folks do something
that I don't know
if I've seen before.
It's actually quite interesting.
They'll take the mid-trained
Qwen3 next model,
and they are actually
just going to train
a whole bunch of
different expert models
for different kinds of
coding adjacent tasks.
And they will end up with
four different agent experts,
and then they're just
going to distill them
all back into the same model.
I can only speculate
as to why they do this.
I don't think I've
seen it in other works.
The closest one I know of
is DeepSeek V3 or was it V3?
V3.5, sorry,
DeepSeek V3.5 or 3.2.
Maybe 3.2.
Sorry, 3.2, I think,
did this thing
where they have different
experts whose only job it
is to format and
process data, so they
have data processing
experts which generate
the data for the full training.
But I don't think
I've seen this thing
of generating
different model experts
and then distilling them back.
That's actually closer to some
academic work like branch train
merge and so on.
Those are definitely
things people do.
I haven't seen it much in
frontier model training.
That said, each of these
experts is actually interesting,
and what they do
is they basically
do full on RL or
and/or SFT training
on a whole bunch of different
subtasks that they've defined.
So they have a web
dev expert, where
they SFT on valid web code based
on different kinds of checks.
They'll do things
build UX experts
trained on many different tool
formats, and they'll have QA.
So the QA agent is just trained
on more synthetic data for code.
But then maybe the
most interesting for us
and the most involved is their
software engineering agent.
And what they do is they
construct agent environments
at scale.
So three benches is
the gold standard
of these kinds of things.
And so what they want to do is
they want three bench but more.
They go out and they have
various automated ways
based on GitHub to generate
a ton of different issues.
And given this, they
want to basically do
RL on these environments in
some ways very unsurprising.
And what do they get?
They can get RL
performance to go up.
One thing I will
say here, and this
is very important through the
broader context of what we're
talking about, the reason why
we can put more and more compute
into RL is because we
believe that our reward
models are unhackable
or difficult to hack.
If that assumption breaks
down, your RL method
will find increasingly obscure
ways of cheating you out
of your performance.
And so they have this great
plot of basically, in Git,
you can look at future
commits or different commits.
And if you have an issue
and there's future commits,
you can just look
up what the fix was.
And this is a very easy
hack for models to learn.
And so they basically
have a whole reward
whose entire purpose it is to
prevent the agent from messing
with the Git history.
And if you don't
do this, you end up
with a plot that
looks like the right,
where it's learning, learning,
learning, learning, learning.
And suddenly, you get
this emergent jump, where
the emergent jump
was actually, it
learned how to manipulate the
Git calls to get the history.
And in some cases, it can even
hack around certain constraints
you give it.
If you tell it, you
can't use Git log,
it might add an origin like
a remote and then query
the remote for what
happened in certain commits.
So there's all sorts
of hacking you can do.
RLVR is only as
robust as your reward,
and your rewards can sometimes
be not very robust at all.
As a side comment, one
of my students and I
were working on a project
that was like RL on lean.
Lean is this formal math,
verifiable language.
And we naively
thought at the time,
there's no way
this can go wrong.
Lots of people have
worked on Lean.
The Lean compiler
is bulletproof.
Turns out the lean compiler
is not adversarially robust.
There are strings
that you can put
in it that will
allow you to verify
proofs that are not meant to
be verified in certain modes.
So I think the notion
of verifiable rewards
is actually much
trickier than many of you
might initially think.
Regardless, you do this process
of constructing these GitHub
repos at scale.
You go through this
process of doing RL,
you see your scores go up slow
but steady, and in the end,
you will actually end up getting
a system that is surprisingly
good, a model that
achieves something
like 70.6% on SWE-bench,
even though you have
what is basically a really
tiny model, a three billion
active parameter model,
you're able to do surprisingly
well on these tasks.
In some ways,
though, I don't know
if this is super surprising.
RL, of course,
you're going to be
able to do well on the
environments for which you've
trained.
You might even
get generalization
to your validation
set as you do here.
But you always want to
be a little bit careful
about comparing performances.
Task specific performance
doesn't necessarily
mean it'll generalize
to broader domains.
OK.
So that's basically all I've
got for the RLVR lecture.
Remember the core
takeaways of this lecture
is it's really all
about the reward for RL.
RLHF and RLVR arguably
they're very similar problems.
But with the difference
being really just
we want more unhackable
rewards so that we can actually
put in much more compute and get
these systems to be much better.
GRPO, at least for the
research community,
is something that really
enabled a lot of this.
And you should all
know GRPO very well.
You should know what
the functional form is
and how the updates are.
This is something
that you should know
as well just
pre-training losses.
And then finally, at this
point, I think lots of people
know how to do RLVR.
As you will find out,
unfortunately, RL
remains very finicky and noisy
and it's painful to work with.
But it's not that hard.
It's not like the old days of
doing PPO on various really
tricky environments.
It's actually a lot smoother
than you might think.
I'll stop here for a moment
and take any final questions
before I let you all go, in
case anyone has questions.
A really quick
question-- when you
mention about the models being
in thinking mode on and off,
is the wait on the model
or [INAUDIBLE] the same?
Or do they play prompting or do
they have different underlying
models that they call back?
Yeah.
So the question was
about thinking mode
and what's happening
on the back.
So the interesting thing
about thinking mode really
is that it's actually one model.
And there's just a
little prompt tag
that switches them between
long and short, like long COT
and no coat almost mode.
Whereas if you just had an
API flag or something, that's
not very difficult.
The fact that
they were putting both
of them in together
is the interesting bit there.
So you can actually
choose, [INAUDIBLE]
but then you add extra
prompt yourself to do COT?
Yeah, or the control mechanism
in this case is in the prompt
rather than at the API or
serving layer or something
like that.
Yeah.
Great.
Oh, yeah.
So you mentioned the
phase of the mid training.
I was wondering how much
of the formatting that
goes into the mid
training process,
informs what is able to be
learned during the RLVR post
training and then as a secondary
to that question of if you don't
have the correct
data in mid-training,
then is it safe to assume that
the reinforcement learning can't
sample a correct solution and
therefore you can't learn it?
Yeah.
So the question was about the
role of mid-training in RL.
I think there are a lot of
empirical subtleties here.
I don't have a
one size fits all.
It will definitely
not work an answer,
but to give a little
bit of the nuance,
I think pre-training
and SFT are doing
a lot of the heavy lifting.
As long as you have coverage,
if pre-training just
doesn't have any code data,
then you're in trouble.
You need training.
But if your pre-training was
very diverse and it covered,
let's go back to the
mid-training slide.
If it covered a lot of
stuff like text code data
and it covered a
bunch of GitHub data,
then this is very nice to
have, but maybe not critical
because you're
going to SFT anyway,
and the SFT will allow you
to get close enough to start
getting some rewards for RL.
If you didn't have SFT, then
you're in DeepSeek trouble.
But the fact that
we're always going
to be doing some amount of
SFT pre RL really helps you,
and pre-training
has enough coverage,
hopefully that
you're able to get
some reasonable generalization.
So mid-training is
very nice to have.
Very important in order to get
slightly better generalization
but not necessarily
make or break, I think.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] there is a step
after train your transfer model.
We're going to be still jumping
into a single model at the end.
So does that-- how does this
kind of distillation work?
Do you have to design
a mixed procedure?
Yeah.
So that's right.
So distillation
procedure is going
to require you to write
down a sequence of prompts
on which the experts will be
distilled into the final model.
Yeah.
I can definitely
see the advantages
of this approach,
which is that you
can have a separate team
working on each expert.
It's much easier to
have teams work on this.
And then the aggregation could
potentially be simple as well
if you have enough compute.
It's just that this-- if
you have all the objectives,
you might as well just throw
it into the big training loop.
Usually, I think that's how
you would prefer to do things.
That way, you don't have to
deal with this distillation
complication.
You could just have one big
training objective that you then
do one training loop.
Yeah.
Is the long reasoning
training also part
of the training,
that mid-training?
So the question was, is
the long reasoning training
part of mid-training.
So I think so there's long COT
SFT in both R1 and Kimi K5.1.
Long COT is not traditionally
part of mid-training, per se,
but it is often--
long COT like data is used
in long context extension.
So it's a little
bit more subtle.
I didn't talk about long
context extension at all
and I regret that.
But usually, that's an
additional phase right
before RLHF or other
things, in this case,
also long COT where you
extend the context using
any long context data you have.
Usually, it's a combination of
books, code, synthetic data,
because those are the
things that are long enough
to do extension on.
Yeah.
So like I guess related to this
diagram that's currently up,
when you're doing this
[INAUDIBLE] process,
let's say how much math,
chemistry, many other domains.
Is it common to do it
in parallel, with one,
I guess, like reinforcement
learning training run?
Or you do it sequentially?
And if you do it
sequentially, how
do you avoid forgetting
earlier parts of the learning?
Yeah, I think the closest
answer to this question
do you do things
sequentially or in parallel
is these diagrams, where
the two splits that you
do is you split
amongst like reasoning
problems and
non-reasoning problems,
and the reasoning problems
all go in one bucket
and they get
executed at stage II.
And then the non
reasoning problems
happen at the final RLHF phase.
And this includes
stuff like chattiness
and so on and so forth.
And those all go into
the one later bit,
which is the stage IV.
OK.
Great.
Thanks a lot.
See you next week.
[APPLAUSE]